OLUGBENGA PAUL KAYODE

SUMMARY

Accomplished, self-motivated. fintech, enterprise technology and business development leader with over 15 years of professional experience across electronic channels in payment and settlement systems, IT operations management, digital products and platforms innovation implementation from conception to roll-out, project management with agile focus, regulatory compliance as well as multi-disciplinary teams, vendors and customer success management.

CONTACT

PHONE

- +234 809 876 6741
- +234 815 423 8886

LINKEDIN

www.linkedin.com/in/olugbengapaul -kayode

EMAIL

Paulkayode1@outlook.com

HOBBIES

- Playing the piano
- Indoor sports
- Payment systems advisory
- Beach clubbing & hiking
- Digital Payment Systems Advisory

EDUCATION

Master of Business Administration

Edinburgh Business School | Heriot Watt University, UK

Bachelor of Science (Hons) in Industrial Mathematics

Industrial Mathematics | Second Class Upper Division

Senior Management Program

Lagos Business School

[Certified E-Commerce Consultant (CEC), Member, Nigeria Computer Society (NCS), Chartered Management Consultant, IBM Certified Data Science Professional]

CORE COMPETENCIES & SKILLS

SOFT

- + Leadership and Mentorship: Emotional intelligence, team building, motivation, delegation, performance, time management and prioritization, organization and coordination of resources, understanding and influencing people
- Business Development: Strategy and vision, identifying opportunities, effectively building and managing relationships, data-driven decisionmaking, target and P/L ownership, lead generation, qualification, and streamlining conversion processes for optimized growth.
- → Product Management: Conceptualization, development, roll-out and lifecycle management
- ← Communication: Effective written and verbal communication across technical and non-technical audiences, advanced presentation skills
- + Strategic Thinking: Business acumen, identifying technology opportunities, aligning IT with business goals
- Problem-Solving and Adaptability: Analytical and critical thinking, identifying root causes, implementing solutions, dispute resolution, negotiation and contract management and continuous learning
- → Project Management: Planning, execution, risk management, budget control

TECH

- + Enterprise Design, Data Centre Management, Cloud Technologies and Business Continuity
- Application Support & Development: Agile methodologies, API integration, Scripting and Automation [Python and NodeJS]
- Digital Payment Products: Payment Processing Systems, Card Networks, Fraud Management, Regulatory Compliance
- ✦ Remote Working Tools: Teams, Slack, Zoom
- Web Technologies, UI/UX optimization, Linux, Windows and Office Productivity tools
- ★ Large Language Models (LLM) and Generative AI, Biometric Systems and Data Analysis
- → EMV, ISO20022, ISO8583, XML, JSON and API Engineering

INDUSTRY AFFILIATIONS: At various times member of the Committee of Heads of Banking Operations (CHBO), Committee of e-Banking Industry Heads (CeBIH), Board for ACH, Instant Payments, Card Payments Industry Working Committee, Vison 202020 Working Group on Settlement and Collateral Management, and the AFRIGO national payment card implementation committee.

WORK EXPERIENCE

1. Nigeria Inter-Bank Settlement System Plc: Assistant Vice President and Head, Fintech Institutions Business Development

10/2021 - 12/2023

Led the Fintech Institutions division of the Business Development Directorate to grow the sector with licensed payment service providers such as Switching companies, payment solutions service providers (PSSP/PTSP), Mobile Money Operators (MMO), Super Agents, Stock Market players, International Money Transfer Operators (IMTO), Payment Service Banks (PSB), and other partners via collaboration, co-creation and assisting fintech startups to integrate faster into digital financial technology platforms and streamline digital financial products to suit each partner for a win-win business synergy.

Key Responsibilities

- Drive overall fintech business growth to achieve set budget for partner onboarding and revenue targets and develop strategies to achieve them.
- Develop and implement business development plans via comprehensive plans and pipelines, allocating resources and setting KPIs for the team.
- Foster collaboration and team synergy by align the team with product management, operations and technology teams and ensure seamless onboarding for customers and smooth inter-departmental communication.
- Monitor and analyze performance: Track individual and team performance against targets, identifying areas for improvement and implementing corrective actions.
- Resolve customer issues: Escalate and address customer concerns efficiently, ensuring high client satisfaction.

Major Achievements

- Onboarded 89% onboarding of all eligible licensed partners
- Onboarding of all the 18 southern state governments on at least one DFS service through collaboration with fintech partners
- Worked with the Product Management team to digitalize the industry account-based Direct Debit Mandate System for central authorization
- Grew the new business division's revenue from N450 million at the end of 2021 to N3 billion at the end of 2023

2. Nigeria Inter-Bank Settlement System Plc: Head, Technology Operations

07/2019 - 10/2021

Led the day-to-day core technology and operations teams of the company:

- Nigerian Central Switch Operations [Instant EFT and Bill Payment over the Web, Mobile, USSD and ATM
- + Payment Terminal Services Aggregator (PTSA) Operations [payment cards interoperability, routing as well as merchant/acquirer/issuer/switch/PTSP settlement and dispute resolution]
- → Nigerian Automated Clearing System [Cheques, Bulk EFT, Industry Settlement operations, e-Dividends, G2P, Fund Sweeping, Tax & other Collections]
- + Identity Management Operations [BVN, Drivers Licence, International Passport and NIN]
- + Enterprise Application Support [Continuous integration of Fintech and PSP partners & API management, Application Issues Resolution]
- Infrastructure [Data Centre, Network, Compute & Storage and Database] Operations

Responsibilities

- Agree with executive management on operational goals and KPIs and, inspire teams to plan, execute and achieve the set objectives
- Proactively mitigate business, operational & governance risks and ensure optimal efficiency

- Manage OEMs, vendors and contracts
- Design and agree all data centre and cloud services KPIs with executive management and implement, monitor and report activities via analytics dashboards
- Accountability for optimal technology systems utilization & ROI
- Liaise with Technology Development to create functional agile teams for product and innovation management
- Provide support to the general-purpose and audit board committees on operations and technology matters

Achievements

- Establishment and daily operations/implementation of the Nigeria Instant Payment version 2, the first and largest instant payment platform in Africa since 2010, with improved efficiency, anti-fraud integration, efficient dispute resolution & faster settlement processing, prompt reporting and instant delivery in less than 1 second with support for USSD, QR code, and NFC integrations leveraging on inhouse development and support frameworks
- Led the teams to implement and achieve 100% enterprise work-from-home capability since March 2020 with proven enterprise-wide productivity enhancement and 100% immunity from the COVID-19 pandemic disruption to technology and operations
- Implementation of the acclaimed Instant Merchant Settlement platform to enable local merchants and agency banking service providers earn real-time values
- Achieved successful yearly PCI, ITSM, ISO audits and certifications
- Consulted on behalf of NIBSS for and provided the knowledge base and expertise to Pesalink Kenya, the Liberian Central Bank and the Ethiopian Central Bank on the establishment of their Instant Payment Services and Automated Clearing House (ACH) development

3. Nigeria Inter-Bank Settlement System: Head, Nigeria Central Switch (NCS) and Payment Platform Operations 09/2015 – 07/2019

Responsible for the operations of the NCS and other digital payment platforms including web, ATM switching, superswitching amongst switching companies, merchant transactions (card and account-based), EFT and e-bill payment services.

Achievements

- Worked with internal teams to upgrade of the instant payment EFT platform with new features for better stability and 99.99% uptime, security enhancements and anti-fraud capability and higher efficiency with less than 0.1% system-based errors
- Grew instant platform volumes and card payment transactions by 85% and 92% YoY, respectively
- Successfully implemented various industry projects to enhance payments and billing touch-points and channels to include USSD, contactless and biometric interfaces

4. Nigeria Inter-Bank Settlement System: Head, Payment Terminal Service Aggregator (PTSA) 06/2013 – 09/2015

Responsible for the end-to-end industry card payment services from merchant, acquirer, issuer and switching company onboarding to PoS payment application and device certification, settlement, reporting and dispute resolution

Achievements

- Successfully project-managed the industry Terminal Management System Electronic Payment Management System (EPMS) platform from conceptualization to roll-out. The platform was used to manage all payment terminal devices in Nigeria for card payments acceptance at the front-end and processors, issuers, acquirers and PSPs at the backend for interoperability and interconnectivity, based on the ISO8583 EMV chip-n-PIN standard.
- Establishment of the value-added system for instant electronic bill payments and notification services on PoS systems

- Worked with vendors to implement the company's first Business Activity Monitoring System (BAMS) and extended same to other industry partners
- Reduction of merchant/terminal details registration across all processing entities from 72hours to 24 hours
- Grew the number of integrated terminals and merchants base by over 200%

5. Nigeria Inter-Bank Settlement System: Head, Nigerian Automated Clearing System (NACS)

01/2008 - 05/2013

Superintended the daily nationwide banking clearing system for cheques and other paper-based financial instruments as well as administered the session-based Nigeria Electronic Fund Transfer (NEFT)

Achievements

- Established regional offices starting with Kano as Branch Manager and later Port Harcourt, Benin, Ilorin, Enugu and Ibadan
- Led the NACS team to Implement the first cheque truncation system in Africa to facilitate paperless and straight through processing of clearing of financial instruments and the elimination of all brick-n-mortar bankers clearing houses
- Led the NACS team to develop the NIBSS Settlement Application (NIBSA) for settling the transactions of Switching Companies, Payment Service Providers, the Central Securities Clearing services – for the Stock Exchange transactions and Card Payment Schemes
- Achieved T+1 clearing cycle from T+4
- Provided advisory support, on behalf of NIBSS, to the Ghana Interbank Payment and Settlement System (GhIPSS) on its ACH business process re-engineering and instant payment prospects
- Provided leadership for the ACH and e-payments policy creation including the Nigerian Clearing System Rules amongst several other published Regulatory Guidelines by the CBN

OTHERS WORK EXPERIENCES

1. Re: Starvision Ltd: Project Manager

09/2004 - 12/2007

- Worked with the technical partners (Industrial Video Co, USA) to design, develop and implement, customize and integrate high-end Internet Protocol based luxury security applications/systems for large corporates built on Microsoft .Net Technologies
- 2. Re: Intercontinental Bank Plc (Now Access Bank Plc): Resident Internal Controller, South-South Region 05/2002–3/2003
 - Provided internal control support to head office on South-South business zone operations covering 5 states (Benin, Delta, Port Harcourt, Bayelsa and Calabar)

3. Re: Oceanic Bank Plc (Now Ecobank Plc): Internal Control Officer

02/2001 - 03/2002

- At various times Internal Control Officer at Head Office Victoria Island and Lagos Island branches in Lagos
 as well as at up-country locations including Kano, Borno, Abuja, Nsukka and Warri branches enforcing
 system, people and procedural compliance
- 4. Re: Universal Trust Bank Ltd (Now Ecobank Plc): Banking Officer

06/1997 - 02/2001

At various times branch operations (cash and clearing) and IT officer